{"tossups": [{"question": "In self-defense, this man murdered a mutinous sailor named Blackton on the island of Tobago. Years after completing his most notable service, this man became a rear admiral in the Russian Imperial Navy under Catherine the Great. When encountering the <em>Serapis</em>, this man supposedly shouted, \"I have not yet begun to fight!\" For ten points, name this captain of the <em>Bonhomme Richard</em> [[bohn-ohm-ree-SHAHRD]] and Revolutionary War hero, sometimes called the \"Father of the American Navy.\"", "answer": "John Paul <b><u>Jones</u></b> (accept John <b><u>Paul</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A conflict in this region began in the Battle of the Bogside in 1969. The Sunningdale power-sharing agreement broke down after a general strike in this region, and a sectarian conflict in this region led to the fall of its parliament at Stormont. Protesters in this territory\u2019s city of Derry were fired on by paratroopers in \u201cBloody Sunday.\u201d For ten points, name this smallest constituent country of the United Kingdom in which the Troubles started in the late 1960s.", "answer": "<b><u>Northern Ireland</u></b> (or <b><u>Tuaisceart \u00c9ireann</u></b>; prompt on \"Ireland\" before \"parliament,\" but do not accept or prompt after that)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Rebellions near Hanguguan led this dynasty's \"Gentleman of the Palace,\" Zhao Gao, to lead a coup to assassinate the emperor. Shang Yang's philosophy of Legalism was the primary ideology of this dynasty, which ended the Warring States period. The first emperor of this dynasty died from an \"Elixir of Immortality\" and was responsible for the terracotta army in Xi'an. For ten points, name this short-lived dynasty from which the western name for China is derived.", "answer": "<b><u>Qin</u></b> [[CHIN]] Dynasty (accept <b><u>Chin</u></b> Dynasty)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A woman in drag named Tullia is nearly hanged by a leader of this empire, Ottone, in a Vivaldi pastoral opera. <em>The Coronation of Poppaea</em>, the last by Claudio Montiverdi, concerns the title mistress's attempt to be crowned queen of this empire. A daughter of a Chief Druid named Norma jumps in a fire with her lover Pollione, the pro-consul of Gaul in this empire, at the end of a Bellini opera. <em>Cesare [[CHAY-zah-ray]] e Cleopatra</em> is set in, for ten points, which ancient European empire?", "answer": "<b><u>Roma</u></b>n Empire (accept <b><u>Rome</u></b>; prompt on \"Gaul\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "In an effort to promote this policy, the Technicolor film <em>The Gang's All Here</em>, starring Carmen Miranda, was partially subsidized by the federal government. The immediate effect of this policy ended the lengthy occupation of Haiti and terminated the Platt Amendment, which had established U.S. hegemony over Cuba. Non-interventionism in Latin America was promoted by, for ten points, which New Deal-era foreign policy?", "answer": "<b><u>Good Neighbor</u></b> Policy (accept Pol\u00edtica de <b><u>Buena Vecindad</u></b>; or Pol\u00edtica de <b><u>Boa</u></b> <b><u>Vizinhan\u00e7a</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Akbar the Great ordered a Persian language version of this work be produced known as the <em>Razmnama</em> [[rah-zem-NAH-mah]], which translates to \"Book of War.\" In this work, a lengthy journey of exile to the Himalayas leads to the death of Draupadi. The Pandava and Kaurava families clash in this work's Kurukshetra War, following a failed peace conference led by Krishna. For ten points, name this Hindu epic written in Sanskrit which contains the <em>Bhagavad Gita</em>.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Mahabharata</u></b></em> [[mah-hah-bah-RAH-tah]] (prompt on \"Bhagavad-Gita\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Near the Syr Darya, this empire's forces burned their entire baggage train during the \"Day of Thirst\" while being harassed by the Turgesh Khanate. Forces of this dynasty's Yazid I killed Husayn ibn Ali to win the Battle of Karbala, sparking the Second Fitna. This dynasty fled to Iberia after being overthrown by the Abbasid dynasty. For ten points, name this successor of the \"Rightly Guided\" caliphs, an empire which conquered much of North Africa and Western Asia.", "answer": "<b><u>Umayyad</u></b> Caliphate (accept al-Khil\u0101fah al-<b><u>\u02beUmaw\u012byah</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's work on animal respiration utilized his friend and human guinea pig Armand S\u00e9guin [[seh-GWEEN]]. This scientist disproved the historically popular phlogiston [[FLOH-jis-tahn]] theory by showing that nothing new is produced by combustion. This man formulated the law of conservation of mass and named oxygen and hydrogen before being executed during the French Revolution. For ten points, name this French scientist who is considered the father of modern chemistry.", "answer": "Antoine <b><u>Lavoisier</u></b> (or Antoine-Laurent de <b><u>Lavoisier</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "Because Septimius Severus was born in Leptis Magna, a former colony of this city, he gave all of its people Roman citizenship at the end of the 2nd Century. Alexander the Great crucified 2,000 survivors in this city after he built an artificial causeway to subjugate its island portion. This city names a type of purple dye from the <em>murex</em> snail, most commonly associated with imperial power in antiquity. For ten points, name this Phoenician metropolis in modern-day Lebanon.", "answer": "<b><u>Tyre</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tyros</u></b>; or <b><u>Sur</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The short-lived Free State of Bottleneck was created in this region from a narrow gap in the Wisper Valley between Allied occupation zones. A brief \"Cis\" Republic in this region was a client state of Revolutionary France before being annexed. A pact recognizing this region's western borders was the principal portion of the Locarno Treaties in 1925. In direct violation of the Treaty of Versailles [[vehr-SYE]], Adolf Hitler ordered the remilitarization of, for ten points, what region in 1936?", "answer": "<b><u>Rhineland</u></b> (prompt on \"Rhine\" alone; prompt on \"Germany\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man established a short-lived Government-in-exile known as the Sigmaringen Enclave. During one conflict, this man's defensive strategy prevented mass mutinies following the disastrous Nivelle Offensive against Imperial Germany. A cabinet led by this man formally surrendered to Nazi Germany during the Peace at Compi\u00e8gne [[cohm-pee-EHN]] following a 1940 blitzkrieg. For ten points, name this Marshal of France who led the collaborationist Vichy Regime.", "answer": "Philippe <b><u>P\u00e9tain</u></b> [[PEH-tahn]] (or Henri Philippe Benoni Omer <b><u>P\u00e9tain</u></b>; prompt on \"The Old Marshal\", \"le vieux Mar\u00e9chal\", \"The Lion of Verdun\", or \"le lion de Verdun\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During the first of these wars, bureaucratic corruption led to wrong caliber shells being outfitted on Admiral Ding Ruchang's ships, resulting in his loss at the Battle of Yalu River. The Treaty of Shimonoseki ended the first of these wars, giving one power hegemony over Korea. The second of these wars began after the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred outside Beijing. For ten points, give this name of two wars between two East Asian superpowers, the first fought between the Qing and the Meiji governments.", "answer": "<b><u>Sino-Japanese</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Japan-Qing</u></b> War; accept War of <b><u>Jiawu</u></b>; accept First <b><u>Japanese</u></b> War or Second <b><u>Japanese</u></b> War; accept descriptions of conflict between <b><u>China</u></b> and <b><u>Japan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "After failing to provide the <em>donativum</em> to this organization, a rogue member of it slashed the throat of Pertinax. This organization auctioned off the title of <em>imperator</em>, eventually bestowing the title to Didius Julianus for 25,000 <em>sesterces</em>. Earlier that year, this elite unit's prefect paid off Narcissus to kill his wrestling partner, Emperor Commodus. For ten points, name this imperial bodyguard who often interfered in Roman politics.", "answer": "<b><u>Praetorian</u></b> Guard (accept <b><u>Praetorian</u></b> Cohort; accept Cohort\u0113s <b><u>praet\u014driae</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "In 2015, in the area surrounding this waterway, an Economic Zone was established with custom rates set at zero as part of a larger \"Area Development Project.\" Operation Musketeer was a planned invasion of this structure by Britain and France, which occurred during a \"Crisis\" around this structure's nationalization by Gamel Abdel Nasser. For ten points, name this waterway that connects the Mediterranean Sea and the Red Sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Suez</u></b> Canal (or Qan\u0101tu as-<b><u>Suways</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Pliant Mahon [[PLY-ant muh-HAHN]] received a fourteen-year prison sentence during this conflict in which Deputy Bill Dempsey was killed by Frank Phillips. This conflict escalated over the failure of Perry Cline to win a lawsuit regarding a deed of land. Jim Vance may have started this conflict, in which one side\u2019s cabin was burned during the New Year\u2019s Massacre. Figures like Randolph \"Ole Ran'l\" and \"Devil Anse\" took part in, for ten points, what feud between two rural families in West Virginia and Kentucky?", "answer": "<b><u>Hatfield-McCoy</u></b> Feud (accept <b><u>Hatfield-McCoy</u></b> War; accept the <b><u>Hatfield</u></b>s and <b><u>McCoy</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Taney [[TAW-nee]]-era case <em>Strader v. Graham</em> held that this law's prohibition of slavery did not extend to states created from the territory it covered. Little Turtle's War was fought in the territory created by this act, which mandated appointments for governors and population thresholds for future statehood. For ten points, name this organic act that established a namesake territory between the Mississippi and Ohio rivers.", "answer": "<b><u>Northwest</u></b> Ordinance (or An Ordinance for the Government of the Territory of the United States, <b><u>North-West</u></b> of the River Ohio; accept <b><u>Northwest</u></b> Ordinance 1787; accept <b><u>Northwest</u></b> Ordinance 1789; accept <b><u>Northwest</u></b> Territory)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country's 1960 independence was established by the London and Z\u00fcrich Agreements. One leader of this country survived four assassination attempts and was given the title \"Ethnarch.\" This country, whose first president was Makarios III [[mah-KAHR-yohss the THIRD]], pursued a union with a larger country in a process called <em>Enosis</em> [[ee-NOH-siss]]. This country's north has been occupied since 1973 by Turkey and is divided by the Green Line. For ten points, name this island nation, controlled successively by the Ottomans and Great Britain, in the eastern Mediterranean.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Cyprus</u></b> (or <b><u>Kypriaki</u></b> Dimokratia; or <b><u>Kibris</u></b> Cumhuriyeti; accept <b><u>Kypros</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During World War Two, this composer served his local community as a fireman, and although he was denounced several times by Josef Stalin, this composer joined the Communist Party of the Soviet Union in 1960. This composer had to premiere one piece in Kuybyshev [[KOY-bish-shev]] after being evacuated due to a Nazi siege of a Russian city. For ten points, name this Soviet composer of the \"Leningrad Symphony.\"", "answer": "Dmitri <b><u>Shostakovich</u></b> (or Dmitri Dmitriyevich <b><u>Shostakovich</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This thinker debated fellow pragmatist John Dewey after publishing</u></b> <em><b><u>Democracy and Social Ethics</u></b></em><b><u>. This thinker espoused pacifism in books such as</u> </b><em><b><u>Newer</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Ideals of Peace</u></b></em><b><u>. This first U.S. woman to win the Nobel (+)</u> Peace Prize drew on the ideas of England's Toynbee Hall when expanding the use of \"friendly visitors\" at an institution she co-founded with Ellen Gates Starr in (*) </b>Chicago. For ten points, name this pioneering social worker who founded Hull House.", "answer": "Jane <b><u>Addams</u></b> (or Laura Jane <b><u>Addams</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "<b><u>Near the end of his life, this man prepared the defense of Gibraltar after it was</u></b> <b><u>threatened by the Castilian king Alfonso XI [[the eleventh]]. This Berber's sixteen</u></b> <b><u>month</u> </b><em><b><u>hajj</u></b></em><b><u> to Mecca continued as he joined a caravan aiming to trade within the Il-</u><u>khanate. The (*)</u> travelogue known informally as </b><em><b>The Rihla</b></em><b> recounts this man's visit to Yuan China, the Swahili Coast, and the Indian subcontinent. (*) </b>For ten points, name this medieval Moroccan explorer who traveled over ten times as far as Marco Polo.", "answer": "Ibn <b><u>Battuta</u></b> (accept Abu Abdullah Muhammad ibn <b><u>Battuta</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man delivered a speech condemning Operation Danube, declaring it was</u></b> <b><u>a \"grave error and constituted a serious danger to peace in Europe.\" One of this man's</u></b> <b><u>first actions as head of state was to pass Decree 770 in order to boost (+)</u> population by making abortion illegal. Following this man's overthrow, he and his wife were found guilty of corruption and (*) </b>genocide and were sentenced to death by the National Salvation Front. For ten points, name this Romanian communist dictator.", "answer": "Nicolae <b><u>Ceau\u0219escu</u></b> [[NIK-oh-lye chow-SHESS-koo]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Young Turk Enver Pasha ordered this city's \"September Days,\" a series of anti-</u><u>Armenian pogroms committed by the \"Army of Islam.\" A part of the larger \"Case</u></b> <b><u>Blue,\" Operation Edelweiss [[AY-del-vice]] (+)</u> was a Wehrmacht [[VARE-mahkt]] advance meant to cripple the Soviet petroleum supply by capturing this city's (*) </b>oilfields. For ten points, which Caspian port city was made capital of independent Azerbaijan following the dissolution of the USSR?", "answer": "<b><u>Baku</u></b> (or <b><u>Baki</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This politician and one-time New York governor names a Cornell Law School</u></b> <b><u>building. When David Brewer died, William Howard Taft nominated this man to</u></b> <b><u>replace him in his highest office. This man resigned from the Supreme Court in 1916</u></b> <b><u>to unsuccessfully (+)</u> run for president against Woodrow Wilson, and in 1921, this man became Warren Harding's (*) </b>Secretary of State. For ten points, name this man who returned to the court to serve as Chief Justice from 1930 to 1941.", "answer": "Charles Evans <b><u>Hughes</u></b>, Sr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A \u201cGreat\u201d revolt against colonial rule in this country in the 1920s was led by</u></b> <b><u>Sultan Pasha al-Atrash [[ah-TRAHSH]]. Michel Aflaq [[ah-FLAHK]] created the first (+)</u></b> <b>Ba\u2019ath [[bah-AHTH] party in this country. United with another Arab country in the United Arab Republic, this country lost the Golan [[GOH-lahn]] (*) </b>Heights to Israel in the Yom Kippur War. For ten points, name this country, united with Lebanon in a French mandate and now ruled by the Assad [[ah-SAHD]] family.", "answer": "<b><u>Syria</u></b>n Arab Republic (or Al Jumhuriyah al Arabiyah as <b><u>Suriyah</u></b>; accept Arab Kingdom of <b><u>Syria</u></b>; accept State of <b><u>Syria</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In Galen's [[GAY-lens]] work</u> </b><em><b><u>On Fallacies</u></b></em><b><u>, he criticized this philosophical</u></b> <b><u>school's inability to use clear language and their disbelief in the duality of the soul.</u></b> <b><u>The emperor Domitian [[doh-MIH-shun]] banished one of this school's philosophers,</u></b> <b><u>Epictetus [[eh-PIK-teh-tus]], (+)</u> who returned to Greece and taught Arrian. \"Virtue is the only good\" was often espoused by supporters of this philosophical school. Zeno (*) </b>of Citium founded, for ten points, what school of philosophy which includes the writer of <em>Meditations</em>, Emperor Marcus Aurelius?", "answer": "<b><u>Stoic</u></b>ism (or <b><u>Stoic</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was subpoenaed for his knowledge of Operation Red Dog, a neo-Nazi</u></b> <b><u>attempt to seize the island of Dominica in the early 1980s. This man is the oldest</u></b> <b><u>person to receive an electoral vote, which he received from Bill Greene in the 2016</u></b> <b><u>election. This first chairman of the (+)</u> Citizens for a Sound Economy organized the early Tea Party protests in the 2000s. The (*) </b>father of Kentucky senator Rand is, for ten points, which Libertarian presidential candidate, a former representative from Texas?", "answer": "<b><u>Ron Paul</u></b> (or <b><u>Ron</u></b> Ernest <b><u>Paul</u></b>; prompt on \"Paul\" alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Despite being a Muslim beylik [[beh-\"LICK\"]], the flag of Karaman features a</u></b> <b><u>prominent blue one of these symbols on its official ensign. The first religious use of</u></b> <b><u>this symbol may be on the cover of the 11th century copies of the</u> </b><em><b><u>Tanakh</u></b></em><b><u>. A (+)</u></b> <b>yellow one of these symbols was sewn onto the clothes of Jewish citizens in the Third Reich as a form of identification. The flag of (*) </b>Israel depicts, for ten points, what six-sided shape named for the victor over the giant Goliath?", "answer": "<b><u>Star</u></b> of <b><u>David</u></b> (or <b><u>Magen David</u></b>; accept <b><u>Shield</u></b> of <b><u>David</u></b>; accept <b><u>Seal</u></b> of <b><u>Solomon</u></b>; or <b><u>Ring</u></b> of <b><u>Solomon</u></b>; or <b><u>Kh\u0101tam Sulaym\u0101n</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}], "bonuses": []}